Hello, I'm your host David Bernard and
with me today, Revenue Cat CEO Jacob
Iding. Our guest today is Eric Crowley,
a tech investment banker with GP
Bullhound, where he provides transaction
advice and capital to top companies in
the consumer subscription software
space. On the podcast, we talk with Eric
about the opportunities and challenges
of AI for consumer apps, what you can
learn from Straa acquiring Rena, and the
flawed thinking around subscription
fatigue. Hey Eric, thanks so much for
joining us on the podcast.
>> Thanks David. Thanks Jacob, thanks for
having me again. Always a pleasure.
>> And Jacob, nice to have you on as well.
>> Good to be here.
>> So this is our fifth time to have you
on. this is your fifth or sixth uh
consumer subscription software report.
So I realized in the last few episodes
having you on I've assumed certain
knowledge of the audience but I didn't
want to do that this time. So let's just
kick it off with what is your uh famous
uh and infamous consumer subscription
software report that you do every year.
Why do you do it and what is GP
Bullhound?
>> Yeah, let's let's we'll work backward
from that real quick. So keep the
commercial short. uh GPhound, we're an
investment bank and venture capital
fund. Uh been around for 25 years.
Offices in New York, San Francisco, uh
which is where I sit in SF and then uh
nine offices all around Europe. And we
we are the uh only investment bank with
a focus on consumer subscription
software companies. It's a big chunk of
our business. We almost exclusively
focus on selling uh companies mostly for
entrepreneurs. We're helping them raise
capital and we'll talk about a couple of
the deals we've done in the past. So
that's the firm. I started our CSS
practice back in 2018 actually when we
sold all trails uh to Spectrum Equity
and that was kind of the eye openening
moment for me about the power of selling
software to consumers. I think a lot of
people in 2018 were like B2B SAS B2B SAS
B2B SAS. I said that's great but it's
boring. And so I wanted to work with
companies that I thought were fun that I
really got to understand that I could
download and play with. And so I wrote
the first report actually David in 2019.
And so we've been doing this now for for
quite some time. It was pretty bad, but
to be honest, it was the only bank
report about the sector. And we we're a
little different than other banks. We
don't just do
>> That's crazy. Sorry. That's just crazy.
That that wasn't that long ago.
>> I had way less gray hair. That's for
sure.
>> I think that wasn't the first time I I
found GB Bhan. You guys were one of the
first people to put out some sort of
like report or any sort of coalesing of
a quote unquote space here. Uh was was
your uh your PDF.
>> Yeah. you were really early to be so
bullish on consumer subscription to to
your credit and it it's cool that the
origin of that was selling Altra to
Spectrum Equity, but you know it's it's
taken other folks a while to catch up.
So your your reports are like a library
of of the growth of this industry.
>> It really is kind of fun. I mean I think
Jacob, you guys were obviously ahead of
me because you guys were building
building the space before I was. So
kudos to you guys. But no, I mean I
think if you just think about the math,
right? Consumers are 70% of the economy.
They love experiences. They love doing
fun things, right? So why wouldn't
software just become bigger? To me, it
just seemed like a mathematical
certainty that this was going to happen.
And so, you know, I was a younger banker
trying to carve out my own niche. Didn't
want to go play against like 300 other
people that are all doing B2B SAS or or
stuff like that. And they said, "Let's
try something different." And I think I
think that bet's been great. Like I
think we're absolutely thrilled by that.
And it's been it's just been a ton of
fun for me. So, I got to say I really
enjoy my job.
>> Do you think there was anything like
structural or sort of like consensus
thinking at the time for like why this
was overlooked? Was it just like people
weren't used to it? And then like what
has changed from then to now that it's
like cool now? Is it just the market's
bigger? Has like people realized like
churn isn't the worst thing in the
world? Like what's what what do you
think is different now versus, you know,
six years ago?
>> Yeah, I mean it's it's a great question.
I mean the honest answer is six years
ago, right? It just wasn't on people's
radar, but also the companies weren't as
big, right? There weren't nearly as many
success stories. They were starting to
happen, right? If you think about both
Netflix, Spotify were around. People
were starting to subscribe to them. I
mean, think about this. Like Netflix
once again was an OG subscription, but
mailing people the DVDs. So, people were
starting to say, "Hey, I'll subscribe to
something." And but the the success
stories weren't there. So, investors
were not
>> I mean, Dolingo IPO was 21, right? Or
something like this. Yeah. So hadn't
even
>> no that hadn't gone out right. So there
I mean the the market comp was there
right into it was there with Turboax
there's other there's there's examples
you just have to know where to look
quicken right has been around for for 20
years right you had to know where to
look but there just wasn't as many
success stories IPOs the big the big
booms that you're seeing in B2B SAS and
so people were just not thinking about
it but then at the same time right
consumers think back to your first
iPhone you probably were still doing
inapp purchases right probably
downloading an app for a buck.99 right
the concept of subscribing to something
for 20 bucks a year, 30 bucks a year.
That just didn't appeal to most people,
right? And but I think that changed a
lot over the last couple years. One, the
products got way better, right? I think
that's 100% true. I think investors got
super bullish during 2021, probably
overly bullish on some of the CSS
businesses that we saw. And that's okay,
right? You're allowed to get overly
excited about stuff because guess what?
Some of those bets were great, right?
Some of those investments that people
made in 2021 have absolutely been fund
returners, right? Others weren't. But
that's the same for every industry,
right? B2B SAS went through the exact
same thing. AI is going to go through
the same thing. And so, yeah, I mean, I
think where things are now is I still
don't think most investors are caught
up. I will say strategics have figured
this out quick. I think anyone from
media to consumer goods and even B2B SAS
is saying like how do I add on some sort
of a consumer angle, some sort of a
proumer tool to one increase my
ecosystem, two increase my share of mind
share with my target customer. And I
think that's been really exciting. Have
they finally like written off trying to
do it internally like uh like Allah CNN
whatever and whatnot
>> there I mean listen they're are still
trying that's for sure you can hack
these things and put something together
real quick and determine if there's
consumer love and if there is man boom
all of a sudden HBO plus right or
whatever HBO Knack max or whatever your
name you want to call it right that's a
massive step function change for that
business model
>> I shouldn't rag on internal like CSS cuz
that's a clearly a victory despite their
own you know follys
>> they're definitely happy they have it
verse not have it let's call it that way
I was going to cover this uh later in
the conversation, but since uh since
we're talking about it now, you have a
whole page entitled another subscription
question mark exclamation point.
Consumers say absolutely. Uh and I think
that has been a big story which you're
kind of already alluding to is that
consumers are willing to spend and then
it's kind of surprising how much they're
willing to spend. Tell me a little bit
more about you know what you shared on
in the report about this willingness to
pay and kind of the whole idea of
subscription fatigue I think while you
know partially true is is just so
overplayed um so so yeah how do you
think about that consumers are not dumb
right and there's so many tools now to
make sure hey you unsubscribe to this or
or turn off that right so there you
can't trick people right so so I think
like this whole concept of like oh
someone subscribed they forgot about it.
Like that doesn't work anymore. There's
too many good tools, right? And both
legislative plus like just software
tools. And then honestly like consumers
will happily pay for something that
brings them value, right? And so now do
you need like 30 fitness apps? No.
Absolutely not. But you might use two,
right? You might use a yoga plus a
running training app, right? Totally
totally possible, right? And then I mean
the beauty of what's coming up with some
of the AI enablement of both legacy CSS
plus let's just brand new consumer
subscription tools like chat GBT right
that is bringing new value to consumers
every day right and they're they're
going to be happy to pay for that and
they're once again they're making a
trade-off economic time versus money
right and so the value they're receiving
is is real right and so I think that's
what I get really excited about is is
yeah your subscription count probably
went from zero or two in 2018 you easily
have And but like let me take away two
of those and tell me how much you
scream. People be like, "Nope, that's
part of my core. That's oh no, that's
got videos of my kid playing baseball.
No, actually this is how I'm learning
something." Like people quickly say
like, "No, I got value out of this." And
so yeah, I think subscript subscription
is overplayed. I don't think you're
going to have 100, right? But I I
wouldn't be shocked to see everyone
having something between 15 to 20 in the
next uh two to three years, especially
as new categories came up, right? Like
four years ago, no one had an AI buddy
in their pocket. Nobody now, right? It's
one of the fastest growing companies of
all time, mostly consumer.
>> And that's what I always keep coming
back to is like c consumers will
complain. I mean, it's it's human nature
to not want to spend money on things. I
mean,
>> that's a rational market, David, working
itself out is what that is. You know,
you said you said Eric, you said
consumers are not dumb. I would say one
would even say they're rational.
>> Consumers in large numbers generally are
rational over time. Speaking of
short-term irrationality, I've still
been paying 30 bucks a month myself and
30 bucks a month for my wife on Ladder
Fitness, even though I should just
convert to the annual subscription just
cuz 130 bucks in one pop. I mean, I have
the money, but it just feels like such a
big like drop $130, but it's going to
save me a ton of money.
>> I would I would argue though, David, is
perfectly rational, right? Because it's
sort of like you're you're you're sort
of uh implicitly pricing optionality for
yourself, right?
>> Yeah. But overall, it is just
fascinating to see and and you alluded
to it as well that just the products
have gotten so much better and and I
mean I've talked about ladder a ton on
this podcast, but it's just such a good
product.
>> The craft of making mobile apps
continues to sort of improve and there's
always been
>> a design award level apps scattered
around the app store, but I think it's
becoming more the case that that's, you
know, if you want to be a category
winner, you kind of have to be on that
level. And that takes like real skill,
time, you know, from a design
perspective, from a product perspective,
knowing how to work the app store
distribution as well. Like that's a
whole, you know, dark art in itself. So
if we knew the niches that it hadn't
moved into yet and would, you know, we
would we would just go build for them. I
It's hard to predict, right?
>> Yeah, I think I think that's right.
There's more problems. I mean I mean,
listen, think about it now. You're
subscribing to something to help you
unsubscribe to stuff, right? That's a
fact. And then you also have on your
phone. You've now downloaded an app to
help you stay off your phone. Great
business. And you're like, "Okay, that
wasn't a problem that we had five years
ago. Okay, I guess let's just keep doing
that." I want to dig into that more
later when we get into opportunities in
the subscription space. But let's let's
step back and talk about uh Runna. I
mean, another great example of just a
fantastic product that people were
willing to pay for. So much so that they
were growing insanely fast and were sold
to Straa. Now I know you were a part of
that transaction and helped advise RUA
on the acquisition by Strava. So you
can't you know speak too candidly about
it uh but what can you tell us about
that transaction why it happened and you
know some of the thoughts behind it?
>> Yeah so so obviously we were the
salesside adviser to the to the run team
and and big thanks to Dom and Ben and
the rest of the team for for working
with us. It was it was truly a fun fun
deal to be a part of to be honest. Yeah.
So we've sold two companies now at
Estraa. One was Fat Map and then this
one was Runna. And Runna was a
phenomenal business. I mean, they were
kind of the first ones to kind of take I
mean, Running's been around for
centuries, guys. Centuries, right? And
they were like, "Hey, we can build an
app that will keep
>> even longer than that,
>> millennia. [laughter]
Something some guy in Greece,
>> the first person to step on the
Serengeti and see a lion." I think we're
going
>> definitely running, you know.
>> Definitely running. Well, but now and
now that guy has a coach, right, which
is beautiful.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, runner really caught a couple things
and did it really well. I mean, so Ben
is was a former coach for for
triathletes and runners. So he really
knew what the consumer wanted and was
willing to pay for it to get value
advice to get faster, to get better,
right? And then Dom and the team built
just a phenomenal product. Uh kind of
one of those AI native businesses that
that really made running personalized.
And I think like if you have you have to
use the app to truly experience it, but
it'll tell you, hey, you ran a little
slower on this block or hey, there's an
opportunity for you to speed up by doing
a few different things or today you had
this, you know, this you ran a little
slower. Let's think about that. And it
turned into magical moments for
consumers. And then they also nailed
kind of the run club health fit health
fitness trend among like kind of the
next generation where they'd rather get
up at 7 a.m. and go to a run club in San
Francisco versus go out to the bars,
right? And so one, the bars in San
Francisco are terrible. So running is
actually a really good choice. But
anyway, I mean that that materialized
across the world. And so I was lucky
enough to meet those two um very early
on in their journey. And so I was just a
huge fan of the product. And so when
they kind of gave us a call and said,
"Hey, we're thinking about doing a
deal." Um you know, we kind of jumped
right in. And so, you know, when you
think about like why Strava bought RUA,
right? Strava has a bunch of features on
there. Technically, even had some old
training features on there. So almost
almost a competitive product, if you
will. But I mean, I'll give you my view,
right? Obviously, I don't sit within the
Strava board, but this was truly a 1
plus 1 equals 6 acquisition. And that,
you know, people say 1 plus 1 equals 3.
This is way better than that. And so,
what what Strava is is Strava is an app
for athletes, right? And so, if you're
not an athlete, Strava is not for you,
right? And as you a lot of people don't
identify as athletes, right? And so, a
lot of people actually haven't heard of
Strava, right? I'm from Ohio and I can
tell you most of my friends don't use
Strava, right? San Francisco, everyone
uses Strava. It's just a weird world
that we live in out here in this 7 by7
square miles of San Francisco. But what
RUA did is they enabled people to go
from being on the couch to running a 5K
to running a 10K and now they're an
athlete. So for Strava, that's a massive
TAM expansion number one, right? So now
all of a sudden you can actually be for
people that are not athletes but want to
be an athlete and that is a huge TAM.
Two, you know, Strava's done a great job
with consumer subscription. It's one of
the best apps out there. They've been
around forever, great retention. Where
they struggle though is pricing, right?
They were un they have not built in a
lot of different tiers to maximize price
among consumers and runna actually adds
this second tier that Strava can offer
which is a bundle right and we all can
talk about bundling unbundling but in in
consumer subscription it's really
popular with users you already have a
paid user who uses Strava Runa
integrated really well on Estraa from
the beginning even before the
acquisition right and so they were able
to bring an addition ability to upsell a
Strava runner or a Straa consumer with
another package and so I think that's
why it was it was a good deal or the run
of founders didn't need to sell. You
know, I don't think they had to do the
deal, but Straa came calling and I think
offered a pretty fair price for the
business.
>> Well, one of the things I was surprised
at is that they didn't integrate
immediately and that it is being run
kind of as a as a separate business with
this bundle which I was surprised at.
So, any any more color on the kind of
>> I'll give some color and I I mean I I
don't know the Strava folks. I mean, we
know the run. I know both teams but not
super well. But I just think it would be
kind of hard for what what Eric was
saying. It's like, you know, run as a
like come to a thing to like train for a
thing, right? It's a very different flow
versus like Strava is like Facebook for
running, right? It's like you post all
your stuff there. It's where you go to
brag. It's your Instagram, right? And so
it might take a while for them to fully
integrate. That could be true as well.
But I could also see a world where this
is like a better approach like where you
keep them separated and these are two
very different properties and you know
you have a you I don't know if we're
going to talk about it but that you you
talk quite a bit about conglomerates
that are happening and you can almost
see you know maybe that's a strategy for
Strava to kind of play in is where they
they become a pseudo you know a
verticalized rollup company of a few of
these things and then they take
advantage of all the benefits of
cross-selling and things like that.
Yeah, I mean I think it's a good
question. Like you know these are two
very good apps, right? And they're kind
of they're built differently, right? So
and people just say, "Oh, just smash
them together and call it a day." Well,
like that doesn't work, right? Consumers
demand an excellent experience, right?
And both businesses are doing really
well. So if you try to smash them
together and it it's wrong, you just
wasted a whole acquisition, right? And I
think both businesses can learn from
each other, right? Run is amazing at
using AI inside the app. Straa is a
system of record. They don't they don't
have to do that yet. Now Mike and his
team are doing some great stuff. So like
keep your eyes peeled. And then also so
I think Straa has been learning a lot
from Runna on that front two. I mean
Runna does some really good performance
marketing. Jacob's right. It's a little
more episodic. Hey, I'm training for a
marathon. Hey, I'm trading for a big
race, right? Versus Straa is more, hey,
this is what I post my rides on every
Tuesday, right? Those are two very
different use cases for the consumers.
And so I think that uh you know, I think
that's right to keep them separate for
now. And then I think they'll make a
decision down the road when when you
integrate, if you integrate. Any advice
for folks playing in these spaces where
they could potentially be that runa to a
straa where they could be that TAM
expansion, the kind of soft intro. I
feel like we're probably going to see
more and more of these kind of things
happen over time where these giant apps
that aren't necessarily great at aspects
of the broader business that they're
running. It could just be an opportunity
for folks to build these kind of like
adjunct apps and get bought. But like
what does it take to be that standalone
product instead of Strava just building
it in? Like why didn't Straa just build
it in? And how how do you become that
kind of a product that doesn't just get
ripped off by the big guys but get
bought by the big guys?
>> Yeah, I mean it's it's a great question
and it's it's really hard, right?
Because tech even even today now it's
easier to build stuff than it ever was.
It's hard to build something really
great. So what I always tell founders is
if you're trying to build for an
acquisition, that's hard. If you think
about an acquisition, an acquisition is
one company buying one company, right?
So think about all the matching that has
to occur for that. And it's really hard
to build something that is exactly for
one company, right? So what I tell
founders is build a really great
business that consumers love. Just
that's your northstar, right? Everything
else will work out. And let's just say
you're you're running it. Maybe it
wasn't going really well and it didn't
work out with Strava. There there'd be
another suitor. You know why? Because
people loved the app, right? And so my
view is like just build something great,
really get consumer love, and then the
the strategic corporate rationale side
will work out, right? Because people
want to be around products that people
love. And so I think Straa saw that and
made the move. And I think every other
deal I've done with a strategic acquire
has that lens on it, which is the
strategic wants access to consumers that
love a product, period. Right. And so
that's that's gen.
>> Yeah. And to your earlier point, you
know, Rena wasn't in a position where
they had to sell. You know, they had a
fantastic business. And that that's the
most attractive acquisition and the best
place to be in if you're negotiating one
of these acquisitions. It's like, we
have a great business. It's growing. You
know, people love it. Way better
position to be in than than needing a
sale to happen to make the business
work.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. You don't
want to be in that spot ever. Early in
the report, you had a page titled the
CSS State of the Union. And in that, you
talk about a lot about AI. It almost
felt like the whole page was dedicated
to AI and and it's kind of the, you
know, 900 pound meta gorilla in the
industry right now of like what's going
on with AI, how much of it's a headwind,
how much of it's a tailwind. And you
started with the headwinds, and I'd like
to start there. you know what what do
you see as as the headwinds consumer
subscription founders should be thinking
about in this age of AI?
>> Yeah, I mean so this is the first year
we've ever done this like state of the
union letter and we did it kind of cuz I
I was just feeling like man I'm getting
so many questions that are incredibly
nuanced. putting together a slide with a
couple bullets just isn't going to do
it, right? And so I was like, "All
right, how do I write like long form
write what I think are impacting my
clients and hope, you know, future
clients today and and then just think it
through, right?" And like the answer
we're getting from investors every day
is is AI a headwind or a tailwind here?
And the answer is that it's a shitty
answer, but it depends. And and it
depends on a bunch of factors. And so,
you know, we we kind of went through and
just said like here's where we think the
headwinds are today, right? and I expect
that to change materially over the next
couple years. And then here's where we
think the tailwind ones are today. And
we expect that to change materially over
the next couple years. And just try to
list it out. And so, yeah, we we went to
the negatives first, right? Because I
think you got to start you want to start
with the bad news first. And so, the the
big thing we've discovered, and I'm sure
you guys are experiencing this
firsthand, is is Google wants the number
one source of traffic to the internet is
is now no longer the sole default.
Right? So if you're a builder or a
marketer, right, and your job is to get
your product in front of someone. SEO
your your website, your content, that
was it. That was what you did. You the
whole thing you did was optimize to make
sure the Google crawler found your site
and then surface that up, right? And if
it wasn't doing it organically through
SEO, you man, you're putting money into
Google for SEM for search engine
marketing and making sure you showed up
as one of the 10 blue links if you
weren't organically there. All right?
And that applied to business that around
for 30 years. It applies for business
that been around for 30 days. He ran
that exact same playbook and that
fractured a lot over the last two years
and I think it's going to fracture
further where people are starting their
discovery or their recommendation to a
problem they have with with one of their
AI tools. Pick pick whichever one you
want, right? And that is the first time
in probably since Google was created and
maybe 5 years after Google, you know,
came and be the powerhouse where access
to the internet fractured. And so like
it does require a new skill set for
entrepreneurs and marketers to make sure
their products get in front of people
where they can't rely on Google, right?
And so I've had clients, I've had, you
know, buddies that are running
businesses where their SEO is dropping
30 40% year-over-year, right? You're
seeing a bunch of articles come out with
a lot of the major I'll call legacy
publishers that just published articles
on the internet, Wikipedia for sure,
where they're seeing traffic drops,
material traffic drops that will change
their business model. So that's
absolutely a headwind, right? So I think
that's a big a big deal. And we kind of
compared it to the shift from desktop to
mobile where uh you have to really redo
everything, right? And at the same time,
you can't afford to let SEO break. So
you can't just optimize for chatbt and
put a bunch of bullets on your website
because Google still is going to
represent the majority of your traffic.
The question is, does it represent the
majority of your high intent traffic?
And that is what the jury is still out
is if AI is delivering high intent
traffic with clickthroughs. Right? And a
lot of people also, oddly enough,
they'll search on chatbt and then go
search Google for the answer that chatbt
gave them, right? So you're actually
seeing two different attribution is like
one of the hardest problems. You're
seeing two different attribution uh
issues with that specifically. So I
think people are probably actually
underounting how much chatbt or
perplexity or whatever tool people are
using is contributing to traffic these
days. One of the headwinds you didn't
list was that AI is going to subsume all
apps. And I didn't watch the whole
thing, but I saw a clip of Elon Musk
saying that within 5 years there would
not be apps. Everything would just be AI
and the AI would just magically deliver
everything you ever wanted. I don't
think that's going to happen. Any any
thoughts on I I'm sure this is a
question that you posed to yourself and
have had people pose to you. You what do
you see as those real headwinds over the
next 3 to 5 years of AI kind of
subsuming more and more use cases? Yeah,
I mean I think the answer is it's
definitely going to do more. Definitely
going to do more. There's no no doubt in
my mind that whatever you're using with
chat GBT or you know your AI tool today,
it will be more in two to three years
for sure guaranteed. And so then the
question is right like what we we've
heard this the same kind of fear I'll
call it fearongering or FUD like fear
uncertainty doubt about the consumer
ecosystem for years. I think the last
time we heard it was in 2010 2011.
Apple, Google, Facebook, they're just
going to build everything right? No
point in making anything else. Guess
what guys? Game's over. get out. And I
think we're seeing the same thing.
>> Yeah, that was that was the number one
like VC objection for like half a
decade, which was like, what if Google
does it?
>> Google's going to do it,
>> right? I mean, hell, hell, they told
that to Facebook.
>> So funny. You don't hear that.
>> Google's just going to build Facebook.
Don't worry about building Facebook.
Google's just going to do it.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. They probably will build
something that's useful, but I mean,
that's the beauty of consumer, right?
it. You know, there's definitely the
large winners, but you can easily build
a great business that does 10 million in
revenue and pays you 3 million in cash a
year and be a comp and your Facebook
could be a competitor for you for sure,
right? And so, you know, you can get
weather for free on your iPhone, but
it's terrible. Or you can pay someone
and get a lot better information. So, I
think this is kind of like if I'm a
founder, and we talk about this in our
report later, like you definitely have
to have a game plan to compete against
AI, right? I don't think you can say
great, we're just going to do the same
thing we've been doing for the last 5
years and hope to win, right? Because AI
will come after you and they'll come
after you either by licensing data from
you or your competitor. They will start
to build more and more functionality in
there that people will just start there
and maybe never end up with you. And I
think that's yeah, that's kind of the
competitive threat. We So, we talked
about it a little bit, David, but I
think the page right after our our
opening line was like, hey, we don't
think AI is going to take out the
consumer ecosystem at all. I think it'll
take out some for sure. I definitely
think they'll be losers.
>> This might be a silly question because
we're still early on the exponential
curve, but like has has can you all
think of a single app AI has replaced
for you? Like maybe I could say Google,
but I still Google stuff, right? It kind
of just depends.
>> Google's AI results are so
>> good, too, right? Yeah. You know, you
get you get a little bit of both. You
get some blue links and you get a little
bit of word slop. It's like the best of
both worlds.
>> I often go to Google specifically
because their AI results are so much
better than Chat GPT.
>> Yeah, they're decent, right? Oh, I I
like that they they'll dive into the
pages for you and kind of extract, but
Chad GBT is I was thinking yesterday the
the best LM is the one I can get to the
fastest. I use Chad GBT 10 times a day
or some LM 10 times a day, but I can't
think of a single app that's a daily app
or a weekly app for me that that AI has
replaced. Now, that does not mean we're
not heading towards the Musk world of
full software slop, but like Eric, I
think a version of the argument you're
making is is somewhat conspicuous
consumption, right? which is like people
people want to choose an app. They want
to be a part of an app and it's not just
having the need met. You know, there's a
little bit of like defining yourself by
the software you use and like what you
choose. Um, which I think is an argument
why there are so many weather apps,
right? A phone has a perfectly capable
weather app built into it, yet there's
still a huge industry of of people, you
know, who are interested in in slight
variations on that theme. Will the LLMs
be able to productize the use cases
faster and better than you? And the
answer is probably not at least for a
long time because like why does Rena
exist when you can go to ChhatPT and
have a running coach? I saw somebody
pose that. Like why even pay for Runna
when ChachiPT is a perfectly competent
running coach? Well, it's not a
productized running coach.
>> A perfectly competent running coach
probably remembers what you did the last
time. I mean, those are in theory with
like better memory and more compute and
all these things like in theory solvable
problems,
>> but will it still feel like that
cohesive product? And will people still
be willing to pay for that cohesive
product even when the LLM can like quote
unquote do it? It's not a great
experience.
>> No, it's probably going to produce
whatever crappy version of, you know,
the worst version of a flight tracking
app or not the worst, but like it's not
going to put any care in craft. Now, if
it can, then we've truly reached AGI and
money doesn't matter anymore and like
all that stuff, right? So, like, you
know, Eric's out of job, I'm out of job,
every fine.
>> Yeah. Don't worry about it. We're done.
Call it a day.
>> Yeah. I was like waking up in cold
sweats like 18 months ago about this.
One, I think this is sufficient variance
in it. I think any prediction is like
less than it's not useful to try to
make. And then secondly, I just think
like we've already seen, you know, and
the fact that you split it up in
headwinds and tailwinds, it's like AI is
disrupting. It's certainly like
accelerating some things. It's it's
moving things around, but it's not like
free money, you know, sort of like um
solution for everything. At least not in
the current, you know, in the current
iteration. It's it's obviously like a
next step function um in technology. And
it's a and it's a big driver, I think,
of growth, but like I'm not as chicken
little about it as I was a year ago, I
think.
>> No, I think people are getting there,
right? I think we've heard this over and
over again, right? Like when we did the
flow health deal, everyone was concerned
that Apple was going to come out and
just crush flow. Not even close. The
flow's almost like double the size when
we did that deal, right? So, like I
think I think it's one of those things
where it's very easy to sit there and
scream and be afraid. It's harder to be
the entrepreneur on the ground building
and like I think you got to be smart.
>> I think when the last time Apple did
like a Sherlock truly Sherlocked
something and like it actually
disappeared like I don't
>> they've definitely taken the some of the
gas out of some apps I know.
>> Yeah, maybe that's true.
>> Yeah.
>> So, they might not kill you but they'll
they'll hurt you, right? And they'll
slow your growth, right? And that can
just cause a whole bunch of issues with
an exit, right?
>> But very quickly after the headwinds,
you moved on to tailwinds. And I think
these are the more interesting things to
talk about now that we've gotten over
the the chicken little phase. It's like
how do we then leverage AI to move
faster, to build better businesses, to
build better modes? Uh so what are your
thoughts on that?
>> The first one we see is just in the
marketing like and how you market to
consumers, right? The the ability to do
product testing, message testing, right?
content creation is just off the charts
faster than it was two years ago, right?
And you guys have you guys are working
with tools, right, that are leveraging
AI to do different marketing copy. It
tests that really quickly. And so, you
know, best of breed businesses are
quickly finding like they don't have to
hire 20 marketers to go out and create
content. They can basically spin up a
100 different versions, test it really
quickly to see which one works with
their consumer, right? And delivers the
best LTV, which so not just the
acquisition, but the retention of the
user. That's been really powerful. two,
you know, you can spin up new features,
new content even faster with some of the
coding tools, right? So, effectively,
you know, if you think about how long it
took all trails to spin up their content
with tons and tons of hikes, right?
Ladder, just to use those guys again,
right? Are producing content even
faster, producing new features, right?
Enabling their coaches to produce more
content. So, to me, like you're going to
create a much better much better version
of the business real quickly, and you
can spit up new features that consumers
love. If you see like a little bit of a
tick where people are starting to use
different things, I think I think that's
pretty cool. And then, you know, the the
moes are hard, right? It's really hard,
right? And the moes are going to be ever
changing. So, what we recommend is you
build the biggest moat you can. And one
of the things we talked about this year
is like adding hardware or some sort of
product functionality to your to your
subscription, right? Which is
effectively going to move you out of the
competition set for Chat GBT. All right?
If you have some sort of a hardware
piece with proprietary data that's
spitting off it, that's a really
powerful thing. And so Aura, Whoop, you
know, all businesses that have, you
know, raised or are raising that are
going to do, you know, I think ideally
kind of build on their existing business
with AI native features. So I think
that's that's pretty cool. And then the
other one is community, right? I think
the one thing that people don't
understand about a lot of the apps that
we know and love is they are places
other people are putting their content
into that make the apps better and then
we are happily contributing our content,
our energy into those apps to make it
better for us and for other users. And
that is something I don't think AI apps
have done yet. And so when I think about
community, you know, I think that's also
includes like the concept of brand and
trust, right? And so inputting very
personal information about yourself. And
we all know people put really personal
information into chatbt or prefer to get
a lot of personalized information out of
chatbt with some of the erotic
functions. People are going to continue
to work within their own app and what
they know and love. And so I think
people are building community, really
strong brand, really strong design,
right? Because like using something on
your phone can be really painful if it
sucks, right? But something that's
beautifully designed, intuitive, right?
That's what gets people to come back and
use those products over and over again.
So I I think like the combination of AI
plus human insight to build a beautiful
product is going to be, you know, the
way to win long term.
>> Yeah, I really love the way you summed
up this state of the union. So I'm going
to I'm going to read the quote because I
thought it was so good. The future will
be built by those who combine AI's power
with enduring human insights and design.
Creating products that people not only
use but refuse to live without and
choose to evangelize to their friends.
Like that's your goal as a consumer app
builder today in 2025 is to leverage AI
to build those great things. And and the
moat, like you said, is so many
different ways to build modes, but that
great user experience being that
incredible intuitive experience on this
tiny little pocket supercomput, it is
just so powerful.
>> Completely agree.
>> The next thing I wanted to talk about
was uh you had a whole slide about the
walled gardens opening up and then
fascinatingly since you published the
report, Google had to comply with the
injunction in the Epic v. Google lawsuit
and they opened up way more than Apple
even opened up. So, it has been a big
story this year of the app stores really
loosening up. What What are your
thoughts and what are you seeing on the
ground as far as how this is actually
playing out and actually helping
consumer subscription businesses?
>> The app stores absolutely add value to
the to consumer subscription businesses
for sure. Right. Absolutely value. I
think what the world has woken up to is
that there's probably a limit on that
value. And so I think the lawsuits that
have been coming for the years, right,
are finally starting to take impact. But
also people are moving now. So like
three or four years ago, most people
were not worried about getting outside
the app store. Just wasn't a function.
They said, "Great. I'm, you know, I'm
going to pay 30% and call it a day."
That was for two reasons. One, it was
kind of hard to build a third payment
rail and go through building all that
tech and working on web funnels. Like
that was hard, right? So if you weren't
big enough or hey, the business is
working great, why do something hard,
right? Just don't fix what isn't broken.
But then I'd say like the last two
years, every one of my clients, and I do
mean everyone, is building web funnels.
And I think one, they're just not as
worried about Apple coming after them or
being being mean, right? And we've all
heard stories about product updates
getting jammed up and going through
multiple rounds of reviews because you
had a link out to a different payment
tool. And Apple got their hands slapped
and they got their hands slapped hard
for doing that, right? And I think that
was kind of proven that they were kind
of jamming people up a little bit. And
so I think one that they've kind of
said, "All right, great. We're going to
back away from that." Right? So, you
know, people that are building apps of
scale, right? Getting 15 to 20% of your
profit margin back is a big deal, right?
It's a big deal. And so, when you're
especially when you're 100, $200 million
in revenue, we're talking about multiple
million dollars in profit. And so, like,
it's crazy not to build for that. And
so, I would tell you, every one of my
clients is now, if they haven't built a
webunnel, they're actively looking at
it. You know, I think we've seen a lot
of payment providers come up there like
Paddle, Solid Gate, you know, Stripe
even that are helping people kind of
manage subscription payments, manage the
tax withholding, all that type of stuff.
Uh, that automates once again what was a
hard problem to do, right? I think even
you guys were thinking about doing
something on that front. And so I I
think that's really exciting. And then,
you know, I think people just said like
the fear of Apple's going down a little
bit. They're still super valuable
partner. You know, most people will
never, you know, throw up their hands
and leave, but I think the word is out.
Hey guys, like it's okay to build for
this stuff and it's easier to do it than
ever. So why not go pick up that money?
So that's that's what I'm seeing on the
ground. the operative question and the
way you you presented it in your um
slide deck is you know I don't what the
split was certain amount of billions
that goes to developers net versus you
know what goes to Apple and that's
actually where we'll see I mean if we
have good data on total revenues uh
versus like Apple reported app store
revenues um if there's is a substantial
shift in this I think one of the one of
the challenging things I've seen with
folks adopting this stuff is you know
just the time it takes to port things
over. You know, it's not something you
can do overnight, especially if you have
like an established subscriber base and
and things like this. But yeah,
basically anybody anybody past a million
dollars a month, maybe even less than
that, is is probably should be or is
doing some amount of this. But yeah, I
think my my biggest and and maybe now
that Google has, you know, complied as
well and and maybe this is like a new
market equilibrium. It's still early on
if this is going to stick, but maybe it
will. Now, now that I feel like Google's
there, too, like it might like I don't I
don't know. I mean, I think it would be
hard even from a competitive perspective
for Apple to to regress, but you know,
the the court order and we've said this
on the pod in the US before is like
extremely against Apple in the sense
that they don't they basically they're
required to provide distribution for for
basically zero uh requirements on the
developer. I don't expect that to last,
but it doesn't mean they're going to get
substantially worse. I I was uh trying
to use NordVPN recently and saw how they
do it. And they're not required to have
a link to the App Store plans like on
their payw wall, but they do. And I
think that's probably either by by fiat
or by sort of market forces where we'll
end up is that, you know, the big apps
will kind of subtly push you to this
like off app store payment, but the uh
the app store payment may still be
available. But I don't know if the case
gets fully like played out and this
injunction gets resolved and and
whatever, we end up with some sort of
like more stabilized case law on this. I
almost think Apple's just going to, you
know, we've talked about it's just going
to have to drop the price, right?
They're just going to have to drop to 20
or 15 or whatever number is going to get
them to their like new market optimal,
which I would call that a win, right?
Like if Apple just has to like set the
price to a point where developers will
opt into it, I think we'll be in a
better position than we were with a
higher fee. Apple won't, but also it's
like the app for business is at scale.
They at some point they have to
understand that there will be some
margin erosion, right? So maybe I'm
maybe I'm coming around maybe I'm coming
around on this.
>> Yeah, we we've talked about it a lot on
previous podcasts and Twitter and other
places as well. So I won't rehash all my
thoughts on it, but just just to to get
a few jabs in here. I think you stated
it really well is getting 15 to 20% of
your margin back because too many people
are talking about it as if you instantly
day one get 30% of your margin back by
getting rid of the 30% fee and we know
that's not true and then plus you know a
lot of these more mature consumer
subscription businesses are already at
15% because Apple drops it to 15% at
year two and then Google has been 15% on
consumer subscriptions across the board
even first year on consumer
subscriptions for several years Now, uh,
so the margin opportunity isn't as big
as it first seems. And then there's also
businesses that I think work better in
this way. Like certain businesses
function better with a web funnel.
Certain businesses just need that in-app
experience to convince people. And then
consumers like it's going to be
interesting to watch of how, you know,
people have gotten very comfortable with
converting in the app store because they
have that power. They know exactly where
to go. they know how easy it is to
control the subscription and is that
comfort level valuable enough and how
much margin hit do you take just on
those conversions and then retention
like there's so many factors and so even
though it seems like such a slam dunk
it's not always the slam dunk and not
necessarily lowhanging fruit for all
businesses but the great thing is like
now it's an option so now it's like for
the right business
>> I mean it's definitely working for a lot
of people though at this point like you
know we're beyond experimentation phase
and like a lot companies have made it a
part of their their thing. I still, you
know, go back to my normal cautions not
to do this too early and think you're
going to like magically, but like it
seems there's definitely uh spread there
for some scale or from some class of
large scale businesses.
>> Well, and speaking of uh regulation, the
click to cancel law got stalled out.
That was a interesting concept of
legislation. It's one that the market
doesn't need. And I say this because
like every one of my clients knows that
like if you make it hard to offboard,
you're going to get sued, right? Think
about like all the gyms that are getting
sued. Amazon Prime's gotten sued for
making it hard to offboard. And like it
creates a bad blast experience for a
consumer. It does because now they're
pissed at you. You wasted them 30
minutes, right? So like make it easy to
offboard. Make it super easy to onboard.
Don't forget about marketing to those
consumers, right? Like we call it
remarketing. Um right? So you have a
huge base of churned users. every
company does. Like that's that's someone
who loved you at one point to pay you
money. There's a good chance you can get
them back, right? You just got to offer
them something different or remind them
of the value of the great times you had
together. But if you make it bad at the
last couple minutes, like guys, this
it's just a bad move, right? It's
shortsighted, right? And I think almost
every client that I have that's building
a best of breed client or best breed
product has figured that out. Yeah. So I
think that's one of those things like
great by the time that law if it does
get passed, it's going to be old news.
The only thing that I still wish it had
gotten past was to kind of, you know,
you're talking to and interacting with
Best of Breed, but there are certainly
tons of businesses that are still trying
to make it harder to cancel and they
care about the revenue. They don't care
about that bad experience because
they're optimizing for a different kind
of business. And then the unfortunate
part there is that then it does kind of
sour consumers generally to
subscriptions. And that that's the one
thing that I I did was looking forward
to if that law passed was that it would
kind of clean up some of the bad
practices on the low end of the market.
But it's fascinating to hear you, you
know, say at the top end of the market,
it's already kind of solving itself.
>> On the low end, you know, I can't really
speak to that. I think that's a whole
another concept of But I mean, like
credit cards are figuring that stuff
out, right? Like no, you have to be
diligent about it. You can't just, you
know, some people just have a credit
card bills of $10,000 and they don't
worry about a $29.99 charge and probably
right, they probably shouldn't be
spending their time thinking about that.
I think there's a there's a whole world
of like this stuff's just too easy to
catch on your phone. It's really easy to
discover. You know, if you just if you
subscribe to a web funnel, now a little
bit different ballgame, but it's still
attached into a credit card, right? And
so at some point, I feel like that's
that's just easy to track and get rid
of. So, yeah, I think you're just
playing a very short-term game. Well,
one of the things you include every year
now is opportunities. And I love hashing
through this with you a bit on the
podcast because I feel like it's it's a
great opportunity for people to think
not just of building in the specific
spaces that you talk about, but kind of
your thinking behind why these spaces
are opportunities. So, the the two newly
identified opportunities to build
category killers that you list in the
report are Strava for pets and screen
time management. And we kind of already
did talk a little bit about screen time
management, but I'd like to dive into
these these two categories and kind of
why you see them as category killers and
then maybe hints to, you know, what be
maybe future category killer potential
places to play for consumer builders. I
>> mean, Strava for pets is something we
we've thought about for a while and
listen once again we didn't think of it
right for founders have been building
phenomenal businesses in this space
before we thought of it. But if you
think about like once again I think
about like long-term TAMs, big waves
that are impacting the world and health
and wellness is a big one and then
treating our pets like our kids is
another one. Those things are not
changing, right? And they're only going
to accelerate. And so, you know, I had a
German Shepherd uh for a while and had a
had a tractive collar on them. Just
phenomenal product, right? It was one of
those things where like I would get the
notice, hey, you know, you haven't taken
your dog for a walk for a day. Time to
get up and go, right? And that's that
was awesome, right? And I could see how
active they were. When they move into
health, which is something you thinking
about like movement is really tied to
health for pets, right? So, you're going
to be able to get pet insurance, like
based on how many times you walk your
dog, how active they are, if they're
sleeping well at night, right? That is
just going to be something that people
are like, "Great. I spend, you know,
$1,000 a month on my dog for food, for,
you know, I don't know, day classes,
whatever you're sending your dog to,
right? Just whatever you spend your
kid." Like, spending a hundred bucks a
year for that is a no-brainer, right?
So, I think that'll be a big one. And
then the screen time digital focus. I
don't know. I keep waiting for this to
become more popular, but but humans are
really bad at blocking out distractions.
Really bad, right? And when you're
starting to compete against AI, right?
Like you actually got to get better. And
so, I think like to create be creative,
actually do high quality work, right?
You can't have constant pings from the
30,000 apps on your phone. So, I think
there's going to be stuff that's going
to happen there. And then, you know, I
think we're seeing like consumers wake
up to the fact that like certain aspects
of screen time are bad, right? Like most
of my clients are not focused on screen
time and selling ads. They're focused on
doing a job for you and getting you to
close the app as fast as possible. You
know, my wife works for Facebook, so I
can't say that's the same case for all
ads or for all apps. But I think that's
something like consumers know like like
some of the screen time is not mentally
healthy. It doesn't promote good
behavior. And so finding ways to limit
it, especially in kids or young teens,
is going to be huge. So, I'm a big
believer in this in this trend.
>> Yeah. I think that one of the unifying
factors with both of those is is looking
at kind of broader societal trends and
looking for places where people either
already spend a lot of money or have the
opportunity to recoup a lot of money and
both I think those two kind of both play
to that that health and fitness has been
this growing trend and people are
spending tons of money and we see tons
of apps building in that space. pets.
Another area tons of people spend a ton
of money in. And then I do think it's
fascinating how, you know, Opel charges,
I think what, $120, $130 a year. And
their whole pitch is like if you're a
busy professional and you're wasting an
hour a day on Instagram, that hour a day
is worth so much more if you can recoup
that and be more productive. And even if
you're not more productive, if you're
more productive in just like living a
better life so you're not as burned out
so that you're more productive when you
are actually working. It it's like such
a strong pitch. And I think there
there's going to be more categories like
this. And and this is where people
should be looking is like where you know
whether you're already building in
certain spaces or whether you're looking
for a space to build in. These are the
kind of spaces where billiondollar
companies will be built.
>> Yeah. I mean I I fully agree. I think
especially like the one thing I've been
using a lot is is one of these apps. I
won't I won't give them a Well, I guess
Opal for shutting down like email on the
weekends. I mean, I'm not a doctor or an
emergency care guy. Like, there's very
rarely a chance that I'm gonna help the
world at Saturday at 9:00 p.m. It's just
rare. It's not going to happen. But,
man, I look at my email at Saturday 9:00
p.m. I don't need to, right? And so,
like, just shutting that down and then
just, hey, spend time with your wife,
some spend time with your kids, right?
That's just way more way better for me
to do as a human. And so, like, I'm
actively trying to focus on that. And I
think like a lot of other people are
going to realize that same thing too.
>> The last topic I wanted to hit on was
the rise of conglomerates. Uh the
Birkshshire pathway of apps I think is a
a fascinating concept. We kind of
already talked about it with Strava
buying runa and the TAM expansion
opportunities the power of bundles and
things like that but what what's your
thinking on conglomerates in the app
space? And then of course, you know, the
the elephant in the room would be
bending spoons, which just raised an 11
billion dollar valuation kind of running
this playbook.
>> This is something we've been thinking
about for a couple years, and I think we
looked, we kind of coined the term
Bergkshire Hathway, the app store, and I
think Luca actually from Betting Spoon
said they're a combination of Birkshire
Hathway and Google. I think this is a
super interesting trend. investors have
a really hard time wrapping their head
around these businesses and trying to
decide like one what they're worth, two
are they good businesses or not, right?
So those are we we get that question a
lot. We try to frame this in like a
unique idea cuz like a lot of these
businesses are coming up and they have
like high churn products, right? They're
testing like 20 different things and
some of them will fail but two or three
will stick, right? And they'll be really
good businesses and start producing cash
and then all of a sudden they start
building these really big businesses and
so they spend a lot of money on
marketing, right? because they're
effectively getting brand new products
in front of consumers for the first
time. That's hard, right? That's really
hard. So, you have to spend you have to
spend marketing dollars. So, so
investors have been like kind of
confused by this concept. So, we try to
make it something simple. So, I like to
use analogies and try to break down like
how do I think about these new age
consumer conglomerates and and I really
like the business models. I've met with
a bunch of them. They're building really
cool stuff. We use two frameworks. One
is the greenhouse where these
businesses, you know, effectively start
with high-end tech talent, really
high-end, right? They're the best of
breed guys. They're really good at
distribution, right? And they learn
incredibly quickly. So they they
effectively are really good at
marketing, right? I'll rephrase that
word to say marketing. And then they
understand like consumer demand and they
will look for trends and what consumers
are looking for and they will build
something for that. They'll build it
quick. It'll be dirty, but they'll
quickly get it out in front of consumers
and then they'll iterate, iterate,
iterate really quickly. So [snorts] to
me, that looks like two things. One, it
looks like a greenhouse, right? We have
all the the base infrastructure of what
you need to launch an app or grow a
plant, right? You're going to have a
couple things that work really well. All
right. Right. If you're successful, you
have a couple things that work really
well, and there's your cash cows. You
have a bunch of other stuff you'll
constantly be testing, launching out in
the world, and seeing if they work. And
then if they do, they become new cash
cows, and if they don't, you shut them
down. And then ultimately, like with AI,
right, the cycle is happening faster and
faster and faster. So launching five
products 5 years ago, that now looks
like 50, right? And so you can test and
test more and more things. And so we
kind of use this greenhouse concept. So
if you want to invest in a greenhouse,
you have no idea which product is going
to be the best one, what's the top
seller this year, like which rose color
is going to be the most popular. But at
the end of the day, it doesn't matter,
right? So then I tried to look at a
business that like that exists today
that everyone knows and loves that has
the same model. And what I came up to
was Coca-Cola, right? And so Coca-Cola
is a consumer business that's run around
for centuries. They have a great brand.
They have excellent distribution and a
crapload of marketing, right? And so
what they do is is they don't care if
you walk into 7-Eleven in the morning
and buy a Coke or an orange juice and
then the evening you just did a workout,
you do a Power Aid and then the
afternoon you buy an iced tea. They
don't care which one you buy, right?
Effectively you're churning from Coke
every time you buy something else. But
to Coca-Cola it doesn't matter because
they know they have a portfolio of
brands. Some are great, some are cash
cows like Coke, Sprite, Diet Coke that
you will buy once a week for sure,
guaranteed. Others like, hey, you only
need it when you need it, right? a Power
Aid, a Dani if you're stuck in the
airport, right? Otherwise, no need to
buy bottled water ever. And then, you
know, then they'll test a bunch of other
stuff and see if it works, right? Like
Costa, they tried coffee. You know, I
think it was okay. Maybe not going to
work. But, yeah, so those are the two
ways we've been thinking about these
businesses. And so, I've met a lot of
them. Really impressed by the founders
of a lot of them. More and more are
coming up. And so, I I think this is
going to be something investors are
going to figure out real quick. And
yeah, as we noted in the report, like if
Bending Spoons files an S1 and everyone
kind of all of a sudden peers in behind
these PR releases and it's like, hold on
a second, how profitable is this
business? I think people are going to
get really intrigued to kind of find the
next two, three, four of these.
>> Is that the same that's going on inside
Bending Spoons for example? Like are
they sharing like what are what why are
they able to drive much more
profitability than say each of these
brands on their own?
>> Yeah, I mean I think they're just
excellent operators, right? They are
like their model has been initially to
build apps but it quickly pivoted and
pivoted years ago years years ago to buy
and then they buy and optimize right the
definition of optimize has probably
changed over time but they are experts
at pricing they're experts at marketing
they definitely have some really good
tech talent right if you look at what
some of the statements Lucas put out
there right it's a you know where
they're one of the most exclusive hirers
of tech talent in Europe like with the
lowest acceptance rates from job
applications like that means they're
getting best of the best right and so
when you look at what they've done,
right? They're well known for this,
right? And it's well talked about that
they will buy an an app or a business,
right? A subscription business, and they
will fire 97% of those employees within
the first month. And just think about
that concept, right? Effectively,
they're not shutting down the business.
They're not just taking its cash flow.
They are just lifting the business off
whatever infrastructure and team was
done and they're putting it onto their
existing team, right? They're not adding
new people to do this. They're taking
the same 600 people and just adding
business on top of that and running it.
That is operational efficiency that I
don't think I've ever really seen in the
tech world, right? There's no big US
company that's bought a business and
then shut down 97% of their or fired 97%
of the employees without that being some
sort of a massive failure. I think that
they've got a secret sauce and a
playbook that they're running on the
operations side that that most people
have not been able to figure out.
>> Evernote still has 4.4 stars on the app
store, so they must not be going all
wrong. I
>> I think they employed two people from
Evernote if I remember correctly. Might
even be less than that now. That was a
business that had hundreds of people
before the acquisition.
>> And this is just total musing, but I
wonder how much of their what they, you
know, people who build an app and start
it. I think there's a tendency to hold
on maybe too long when you've reached
terminal. You know what I mean? Like
terminal growth. Not that it grows bad.
It's maybe beats the market slightly,
but like the team you built up to invest
to get to that point is not the team you
probably should have, you know, if the
app has kind of reached its like end
state. And and Bending Spoons is just
the the undertakers that'll help you
realize that mission and help you get
over that hump.
>> Yeah. I think they dispute the term
undertaker, but I think they are not
[laughter] they're not
>> I say that in a undertakers are valued
members of society, Eric. Okay. Like
it's an important job,
>> but they are also not afraid to ask ask
those hard questions, right? They're not
afraid to say the person that got you to
a thousand users isn't the person to get
you to 100,000, right? And I think they
they know what it takes to go from
100,000 to 200,000. And they're like
great, we don't need that person anyway,
right? So we're we're moving past it,
right? So I think some people argue
against their model. You know, I think
luckily they they've done well enough
they don't care about our opinions. So
>> Right. Well, obviously they've earned
the, you know, high profitability and
whatever. They don't they don't really
it doesn't really matter what other
people think. Um I'll be interested to
see. I mean, they just they just closed
AOL like recently, which is kind of it
got to be the biggest, weirdest, boldest
uh buy. I don't even know what that
business is, and that's fine. Um I
presume there's some sort of
subscriptions for something in there. I
mean, it's still the number eighth email
client in the world, something like
that. It's crazy if you actually look at
the stats behind it. I mean, it's a big
big business,
>> but maybe maybe still kind of follows
that thesis though of like, okay, like
AOL is this legacy brand that maybe the
the current owners don't really know
what to do with or really know how to
like optimize around for like a number
of reasons, political, emotional, like
all the above. Luke and his team are
just they're kind of ruthless uh and
they and they make it happen, which is
cool. And it' be interesting to see this
old company, Constellation Software. I'm
sure you know of that, Eric, but you
know, there's sort of the like web 0.0
version of this. Like basically like '9s
back house software version. You know, I
I'm I'm sure there's for every bending
spoon for bending spoon, there's got to
be like 10 others that are that are
behind them like trying to replicate
this model in in slightly different
ways. So, it' be interesting to see if
that continues or if everybody just gets
you live long enough to die or get
bought by Bending Spoons. Those are your
two options. So,
>> I think that's a interesting take. I
feel like Bending Spoons is a company
that's most forced me to update my
priors over the last like four years
because initially I did think it was
crazy and Eric and I are in this group
text thread with a few folks where where
we've talked actually quite a bit about
bending spoons specifically and and I'm
one of those and he he was probably
slightly alluding to it of uh people's
opinions because my opinion was not very
favorable early on but I think I see
more and more the playbook as they've
done this is that you know to your
point, Eric, about being able to fire
97% of the people. It's like they their
playbook is operational efficiency. But
then I think secondarily, too, is that
we've talked about a lot on the podcast
about pricing sensitivity and how when
you build a best of breed product, when
you have consumers like Evernote where
you have 15 years of data locked up in
there, that pricing threshold starts to
look a lot different than these, you
know, brand new fresh apps. And then
even the AOL acquisition like which
initially I was like what AOL and then
you start looking deeper into it and see
all that email and guess who guess who
that those you know millions and
millions of emails are boomers and guess
what's a great market to be building
toward and market all those other apps
to boomers. I don't know if AOL joining
or bending spoons acquiring AOL is quite
the runner like oneplus 1 is six, but
maybe it's a very like oneplus 1 is
three or four or two and a half.
>> The joke I made on the internal slack is
uh and I I say this with a lot of
respect for betting is they're building
a museum of the internet. They're
leveraging the museum to bootstrap the
future too because like the museum
people are going in there and then now
you're bundling the Coke and the other
apps and uh and leveraging all of that
into a much bigger thing than any one of
those individual businesses could be on
their own. And then there's so much
power in being able to flip the switch
on IBIDA too of being able to acquire
these companies and and I I would
imagine there's even some financial
engineering around this over time where
>> No, I mean we we're recording this I
think they announced last week, right?
They just did a crazy equity and debt
raise like in the in the billions. So
like they're they're making it work.
>> But some of the businesses they've
acquired, maybe they lay off 50 this
year, 50% this year or 20% this year,
20% next year, 20% the year after that.
And you've just got to dial to dial
IBIDA up and down at will because you
have these retentive really good
businesses with really strong underlying
fundamentals and you can turn the dials.
>> Yeah, we said on our slack, Jacob is how
much would I pay you have to pay you to
drop your Gmail? Delete it tomorrow.
Just delete it.
>> Yeah. I mean, there's some amount of
money, but it's like somewhere around
also pulling out my fingernails level
amount of money, right? Like it's very
high.
>> Like you probably won't get rid of your
first kid, maybe your second. I've had
that email Gmail for 20 years. So like
[laughter] good luck
>> attached to everything, right?
Everything. I mean, you just think about
that and you say that sounds out loud.
You're like,
>> well, thank thank you for the new uh new
thing to wake up with cold sweats about.
I appreciate it. [laughter]
>> Bending Spoons acquires Gmail. It will
happen. It's like uh it's the great
attractor. Like everything will
eventually end up in Bending Spoons. Um
any any other conglomerates you're
watching or upstarts or opportunities
you see in this space that that bending
spoons isn't yet subsuming?
>> Well, on the conglomerate side, I
actually had the fortune to go over to
Istanbul, Turkey early this year. And
first off, man, if you haven't been to
that city, you got to go. It makes like
New York and San Francisco just seem
like sleepy back back roads. It is just
so high energy. It's phenomenal. And I
had a great dinner uh with like HubX,
Codeway, AppNation. And these are some
of the business. They're coming out of
the Turkish gaming culture which is
which has been well known as building
like quick high quality gaming apps and
they're now building consumer
subscription apps and they're great.
They're the founders I've met there, the
business profiles I've heard like won't
give any numbers here, but like they're
fantastic. So we've seen that come up in
a really big way. And then you you got
to ask the question like what do you
build to not you know get bought by
Betting Spoons? And and the answer is
just depends. You can always say no,
right? They're not a hostile acquirer.
>> Everybody who's ever sold the Bending
Spoons has done so willingly.
>> That's right. Yeah. There's there's
there's not too many. They don't buy
bankruptcies, guys. And so, like, I
think that's the way I describe it is
like just build a a product you love and
then you have a choice to do with it
whenever you want, right? And your
community will have a voice in it,
right? Like your employees will have a
voice in it. So, yeah. I mean, I think
that's that's the way I always describe
it to people is like that that is a by-
choice decision.
>> And what do you think the opportunities
are to build the next bending spoon?
Should should people be thinking about
how they can emulate that model in some
ways?
>> Yeah, I mean a lot of people are. Yeah,
it's hard, right? It's really hard
though. Like I'm sure we we've all spent
some time with app conglomerates. You
can't just buy apps and stitch them
together, right? And like what? Like so
you can't just financial engineer it.
Like I don't think that's the solution
at all where you're like, hey, I bought
it for six times, you know, and which
means you're never going to buy anything
from me. But if you, you know, bought it
from six times and then like great, now
I'm going to sell it for 10 times. Like
that game doesn't fly, right? you
actually have to really have a talented
team underneath the hood. Like, yeah, if
you're buying it for six times eBay,
it's probably not growing, right? And
then if you got to like you got to pump
some marketing dollars out there and ask
me how hard it is to market in 2025 to
consumers and I'll tell you extremely
hard and getting harder, right? So, you
have to have a best of breed team to do
that and then you got to do it across
six, seven, eight, 50 apps, right?
That's hard, guys. That's really hard.
So, you know, I've gotten a lot of
people approach me about doing it. I
think it requires like a lot of skill. A
lot of skill.
>> Yeah. And the more money that has poured
into that, I mean, there's so many
companies now buying apps and that means
that the competition for buying those
apps goes up, which means higher ebidas,
which means you got to have an even
bigger win to make the money worth it.
So, it's like it's already hard and then
getting harder by the day as more and
more money flows into trying to build
these kind of conglomerates.
>> You know who the real winner is?
>> Developers. [laughter]
>> I didn't hear what I didn't hear what
David said. But I just heard what Jacob
said. I think Jacob's right. Let's just
[laughter] leave it there.
>> Uh I'm I'm what David's David's the true
right answer. Uh but I do think like the
fact that like apps
past a certain scale has become a fairly
liquid market. Um depending on your you
know your price sensitivity and things
like that is is pretty great. Trading
and flipping apps has always been a
thing. But um you know I think we're
seeing that secondary market for apps
like mature pretty well locked step with
the uh you know and there's good buyers
for these now we're really talking your
book Eric you see more and more people I
do at least on Twitter talking about you
know getting ready to sell flip an app
whatever. Um but yeah I I think I'm with
Eric that the um the idea of like oh I
own 10 apps and now they're worth 12
times what I paid is you know probably a
little bit fantasy. Um, you know, we
talked about bank spoons and stuff, but
like somebody like Elon can go in and
cut 80% of staff, but like you're not
Elon. Uh, is like I think a good piece
of advice for most people. So, really
think about what you're doing. Yeah. I
mean, it always looks easier. I remember
this is such like hubris of builders is
like, you know, you get you start
raising venture and stuff, you're like,
I could do venture. How hard is that?
And then you spend some years around it
and you're like, okay, it's actually
really hard. Most people fail. And I
think that's probably true of the case
of like conglomerates and roll-ups, too.
It's probably most people fail. Anything
worth doing is hard, guys. This doesn't
change.
>> That was so much fun, Eric. Thanks to
you again for joining us. Anything you
wanted to share as we're wrapping up?
>> No, I mean, always, always a pleasure to
be here. I will give you guys a shout
out for your Revenue Cat conference in
New York. I got to tell developers
that's a must attend if you get the
chance. I learned so much. Met so many
great people, had a fantastic time, and
you guys are just going from strength to
strength on that conference. So, I mean,
please keep doing it. I I told Rick,
whatever the budget was, like I'll tell
Jacob, maybe add 20%. What was the
budget, by the way, because you because
nobody will tell me.
>> Good. Good. I think I think it was like
$100 if I remember correctly.
>> I keep asking. People go like, "Uh,
we'll get it to you."
>> It's coming. They're formatting it.
>> I logged into the JP Morgan the other
day, we're good. Good. All right. Cool.
>> As long as there's money in there, we'll
keep
>> I'm glad you still have access to that
app. That's a good one. Hold on to that
one. Yeah. I think that's that's you
know, on our side, I think you have
questions, you want to chat about what I
do is these guys know I'm pretty open
book. So, even if you're not in the
market for selling, like, great, no
problem. If we forgot to feature in our
report, which is the number one
complaint we get, feel free to send an
email to me at
eric.crowley@gbbullhound.com
and file a complaint. I'll send it I'll
send it to our complaints department.
We'll get you added and then yeah, if
you have questions about the report or
want to see it, it's free online uh
gbullhound.com or just email me and we
send it to everybody. So, we love to put
our thoughts on the internet and get
told what we do wrong. So, but no,
always a pleasure to be here, guys.
>> So, is this why you're a great guest for
sub club?
[laughter]
>> Perfect. I love it.
>> Awesome. Thank you so much, Eric. Have a
good one. Everybody,
>> thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
>> [music]